Guide to the University of Chicago Department of Meteorology Records 1937-1950
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Department of Meteorology. Records
1937-1950
1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The University of Chicago's Department of Meteorology was established in 1942, and conducted ground-breaking research through World War II. This collection consists of reports, correspondence, financial material, and other administrative records, mainly related to the department's research and development contracts with the U.S. Army and Navy, with a concentration of material dating from the mid- to late-1940s.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Historical Note
Meteorology as an academic discipline at the University of Chicago began as an institute of the Department of Physics in 1940. In 1942, Carl-Gustaf Rossby organized an independent Department of Meteorology. Early work established the "Chicago School" of meteorology, and the department was the site of ground-breaking research through World War II. In 1961, the department merged with the Department of Geology, forming the Department of Geophysical Sciences.
Scope Note
This collection consists of reports, correspondence, financial material, and other administrative records from the Department of Meteorology, with a concentration of material dating from the mid- to late-1940s. Most of the material originated in the department's instrument laboratory, and is related to the department's research and development contracts with the United States Army and Navy. The projects represented were conducted during and after World War II, and deal with instruments for predicting and measuring air turbulence, humidity, dew point, and winds. Also included are departmental meeting minutes, files on the department's radio station, and records related to the purchase, maintenance and location of meteorological equipment.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
University of Chicago. Department of Geology. Records
University of Chicago. Department of Physics. Records
University of Chicago. Division of the Physical Sciences. Records
Subject Headings
University of Chicago. Department of Meteorology; Defense contracts - United States; Meteorological instruments; Meteorology
INVENTORY
- Airborne Turbulence Indicator, Model M-4, report, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Airplane Turbulence Indicator, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Anemometer research, billing, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Anemometer research, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Anemometer research, progress reports, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Anemometer research, property and supplies, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Anemometer research, final accounting, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bendix Aviation Corporation, Diamond-Hinman Radiosonde, 1942-1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Brissman, D.N., 1st Lt., A.C., “Instruction for Operation of University of Chicago Dewpoint Hygrometer,” report, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Brissman, D.N., 1st Lt., A.C., “A Method for the Continuous Measurement of Dew Point Temperatures,” report, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Chanute turbulence investigation, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Church, Phil E., “The Annual Temperature Cycle of Lake Michigan: II. Spring Warming and Summer Stationary Periods, 1942,” (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Cloud top indicator, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Departmental staff meeting minutes, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- “Development and Flight Testing of a Balloon Radiosonde of High Precision for the Study of the Stratosphere,” report, October 24, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- “Development of Instruments for Accurate Pressure, Temperature, and Humidity Measurements in the Upper Atmosphere, April 1, 1946 to June 30, 1947,” progress report, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- “Development of Instruments for Accurate Pressure, Temperature, and Humidity Measurements in the Upper Atmosphere," status reports, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Endlich, Roy M., Charles J. Neumann, George V. Owens, and Donald R. Purdy, “High Level Humidity Measurements Using Radiosondes with Increased Moisture Sensitivity,” report, July 1948. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Equipment, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Equipment, Navy loaned or furnished, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Equipment, surplus, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Equipment, loans, 1945-1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Ference, Michael, Jr. and Verner Suomi, "Survey and Analysis of Sonic Devices for Measuring True Air Speed," report, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Flight Test Division memorandum, "Modification of an A-4 Camera," 1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Graphs, unidentified, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Insurance, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Hacker, Paul T., “Preliminary Report on Behavior of Lithium Chloride Hygrometer Elements under Conditions of A.C. and D.C. Excitation,” 1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Lake Michigan, bathythermographs, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Lake Michigan radiosonde, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Mobile weather unit, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Moses, Harry, and Ferguson Hall, “A Sea Swell Indicator,” n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Naval research, administrative correspondence, 1947-1947 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Naval research, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Naval research, “Instructions to Contractors holding Office of Naval Research Contracts under the Cognizance of the Chicago Branch Office,” 1947 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Radio set SCR-658, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Radio station, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Radio station, regulations, 1937-1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Scoates, William D., 1st Lt. A.C., “An Airborne Turbulence Indicator,” reports, 1945. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Sea swell indicator, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Services and repairs, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Signal Corps, correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Sonic Thermometer, monthly reports, 1945-1948 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Temperature measurement research, “Final Report on Investigation on Temperature Measurement Contract W 28-003 sc-1618,” report, 1947. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Temperature measurement research, 1945-1949 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Temperature measurement research, final accounting, 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Temperature measurement research, contracts, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Temperature measurement research, supplies, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Temperature measurement research, contracts, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Temperature measurement research, correspondence, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Temperature measurement research, "Investigations on temperature measurement," engineering reports, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Typhoon research (Project TYRENA), 1947 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
- Typhoon research (Project TYRENA), 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Typhoon research (Project TYRENA), reports, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Typhoon research (Project TYRENA), 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Typhoon research (Project TYRENA), proposals, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- United States Department of Commerce, correspondence, 1946- 1948 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- United States Weather Bureau, report, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- United States Weather Bureau, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- W-Sonde, instructions and report, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- W-Sonde, photographs, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 9)